# Bassel El Mabsout

### **PUBLICATIONS**

Mabsout B.\*, Mysore S.\*, Saenko K., Mancuso R. . How to train your quadrotor: A framework for consistently smooth and responsive flight control via reinforcement learning. ACM Trans. Cyber-Phys. Syst., 5(4) 2021

Mabsout B.\*, Mysore S.\*, Saenko K., Mancuso R. . Regularizing Action Policies for Smooth Control with Reinforcement Learning. ICRA 2021

Mysore S., Mabsout B., Mancuso R., Saenko K. . Honey. I Shrunk The Actor: A Case Study on Preserving Performance with Smaller Actors in Actor-Critic RL. IEEE Conference on Games (CoG) 2021

Mabsout B. . Tree Shaping, a solution to the expression problem showcased via a compiler for a programming language named Puler. Masters Thesis, Boston University 2023

### ONGOING RESEARCH

### **Population Descent**

Submitted

A natural-selection based Memetic algorithm which adaptively controls hyperparameter selection via a normalized fitness function – PREPRINT

# Sim2Real Adaptation via Anchored Learning

Anchors allow for adapting RL-based controllers on the fly while mitigating the issue of catastrophic forgetting. Our method does so by finding controllers which satisfy performance conditions both in simulation and reality - PREPRINT

# Safety-critical controller learning

Ongoing

We construct learned bounded Lyapunov functions for maintaining safety under a differential equation and on residual dynamics. Adapting controllers to improve the probability of safety and performance in the real world – **SOURCE** 

# State-estimation using Gaussian splatting

Ongoing

The pose of a quadrotor is estimated by combining Gaussian splatting with an onboard camera feed. Estimation occurs in real-time on the embedded system

# Multi-objective RL via generalized-mean scalarization

Ongoing

We use the generalized-mean for scalarizing a normalized multi-Q-value function forming a continuous specification in a multi-objective RL setting

# **PROJECTS**

### Stochastic dynamics learning BU/MIT

Achieving safer learned model-based control requires accurate models, given most real-world systems are stochastic, we built Generative Adversarial Networks which modeling the distribution of the system's trajectories – **SOURCE** 

### Honda Ridesharing SAIL

In collaboration with BU's SAIL and Honda, we worked on privacy preserving (using MPC) preferential ride-sharing. My responsibilities included defining optimization constraints so users with similar preferences get pooled together

# Seizure Prediction Machine learning -- CS542

A Kaggle competition project which accurately predicted seizure activity in epileptic patients. Utilizing machine learning techniques, we achieved the highest score with a significant margin (AUC score of 0.92) – PREPRINT

Finding a NASH-& Equilibrium Complexity Theory -- CS535 This term paper simplifies an existing proof of the complexity class specifying the run-time of finding approximate Nash equilibria – PREPRINT

Haskell Blog Personal Blog

REVIEWED VENUES

bmabsout.com github.com/bmabsout Google Scholar

### **EDUCATION**

### MS & PhD

09/2018 ---

Boston University

BS

09/2012 -- 05/2015

American University of Beirut

+1 (857) 939-8769

Boston, MA, USA

### MENTORSHIP EXPERIENCE

RISE - Mentored Abhinav Pomalapally via the RISE program performing research in Gradient-based optimization. This work led to his acceptance to UC Berkeley and produced a paper. **BU Spark** – Mentored five students in building a quadrotor for

control research. This project evolved into the Gaussian Splatting research work.

**CS 654** – Created projects for 24 students mentoring them in work that led to research contributions. They modeled and controlled an AmazingBall System while minimizing the sim2real gap

**Efficient RL** – Mentored two graduate students in performing power-efficent RL for pedestrian collision avoidance in Carlasim, balancing cloud and local computation

# **WORK EXPERIENCE**

### Scanman Freelancer

12/2020 ---

Created Scanman, a barcode based inventory tracker acquired by Meathouse to solve long-standing supply chain inefficiencies

## **Zahera** Cofounder - CTO

07/2018 -- 09/2022

Zahera is an app-based photo printing service currently installed on > 15000 devices. I worked on designing the products, building and improving the technologies used, and managing 2 developers

AUB Researcher

06/2016 -- 08/2018

I wrote neural-swarm, a collection of experimental optimization algorithms for learning decentralized swarm control in Haskell

# **CCC** Software Developer

05/2015 -- 05/2017

I worked on the core team of C3D, a leading 3D-based construction project control application. I implemented several key features, optimizations, and bug fixes in the Java based application

# **SKILLS**

PROGRAMMING LANGUAGES (by familiarity) Haskell • Nix • Python • Java • C • Processing • (Java, Type)script • Coq • SQL • Bash • C++ • Elm • C# • F# • ATS • Lean • GLSL • WGSL • Clojure • Matlab

FRAMEWORKS & LIBRARIES

Tensorflow • Pytorch • Keras • Numpy • Scipy • Pandas • Jax • Spinning Up • Pybullet • Gurobi • React-Native • Expo • Megaparsec • Recursion-Schemes • Polysemy •

Firebase

MARKUP LaTeX • HTML • CSS • Markdown • XML • Typst TOOLS Git • Nix • GNU utils • Makefiles • Soldering

### **MISC**

ICLR • ICRA • ROBOT • EMSOFT • COG • DATE • ECRTS • RTSS • TICA

I created a Haskell blog hosted on IPFS about programming language concepts such as automatic differentiation and dependently typed vector construction which garnered some interest and was featured on Haskell News

PRESENTATIONS WASP • Galois • BU AIR • BU Systems Seminar • HRI-EU • ICRA 2021 • and CoG 2021

NATIONALITIES Lebanese and Portuguese